A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Leadership Development Program (LDP), Accession 2017:027 FA1298
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Leadership Development Program (LDP), Accession 2017:027
1960-1980, bulk 1966-1977
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
FA1298
33.70 Cubic Feet 80 LTR size document boxes, 2 Half-LTR size document boxes, and 6 LGL size document boxes
Scope and Contents
The collection chiefly contains Fellow files from the Ford Foundation's Leadership Development Program. Records within the files document the entire lifespan of the LDP (1966-1977), but they also include a few materials collected about Fellows from before and after the program's existence. Fellow files are grouped according to which Regional LDP Office the represented Fellows had to report. The LDP maintained four regional offices. They included the Region-at-Large Office, the Northeast Region Office, the Southwest Region Office, and the Southeast Region Office. The collection also contains a group of Ford Foundation financial materials unrelated to the LDP. Access to the financial materials is restricted.
For the most part, the Ford Foundation maintained two distinct files for each LDP Fellow with one file holding original narrative reports submitted to the Fellow's Regional LDP Office by the Fellow and one file holding narrative report copies submitted to the Ford Foundation by the Regional LDP Office. The print on the narrative report copies is generally of less quality than that of the original reports. If, when searching through a particular Fellow file, users find reports that have unclear text, they are advised to look for better quality versions of the reports in the other file (or files) associated with that Fellow.
Subheadings such as "Reports" and "Regular Reports" were found upon many of the original folders that housed the LDP Fellow files. These subheadings are noted in the rehoused physical folders as well as in the Finding Aid's intellectual description in order to help preserve the original internal arrangement of the Fellow files. However, users are advised that these subheadings do not appear to have been applied consistently and that they are not wholly accurate in describing the content of a particular subsection within a file.
In addition to reports, the Fellow Files are principally comprised of three types of correspondence: 1) Correspondence between individual LDP Fellows and their respective Regional Representative/Program Consultants; 2) Correspondence between Regional Representative/Program Consultants and Ford LDP Staff; and 3) Correspondence between Regional Representative/Program Consultants and organizations that provided internships and other learning opportunities to Fellows. Correspondence generally regards submissions of reports, fellowship progress, fellowship changes, and post-fellowship activities. Some personal correspondence between individual LDP Fellows and their respective Regional Representative/Program Consultants appears as well. These documents generally consist of holiday cards and family announcements.
Also prevalent throughout the collection are materials formats such as newspaper clippings, academic papers, photographs, receipts and financial documentation, classroom tools and learning materials, project proposals and plans, fellowship application documents, publications, pamphlets, flyers, and newsletters. These materials help document the Fellows' program year activities and post-fellowship actions. Additionally, there are two audio recordings that appear to contain the narrative reports of two different LDP Fellows who wished to give oral accounts of their program progress.
Most LDP Fellows were grassroots leaders in the fields of education, social work, economic development, and community organization, and within their program-years, they explored a vast array of issues, trends, and solutions associated with those areas. The records housed within their files therefore relate to such diverse subjects as curriculum development, individualized instruction, humanities education, bilingual/bicultural education, African American studies, sex education, environmental education, special education, child psychology, early childhood development, guidance counseling, vocational education, recreational programs, use of audiovisual materials in education, public housing, public health, drug and alcohol abuse, voting rights protections, civil rights, employment discrimination, minority leadership in public schools, Native American land claims, school desegregation, student rights, child care, student protests, public broadcast television, strip-mining protests, Head-Start programs, human relations, interracial relations, teaching in multiracial classrooms, education for migrant workers, manpower development, teacher education, public welfare, and education philosophy among many others.
Many LDP Fellows originated from impoverished and/or racial minority communities and sought to use their program years to become better leaders for those populations. Thus, their Fellow files contain large amounts of materials concerning African Americans, Native Americans, and Mexican Americans as well as predominately poor white communities in the Appalachian Mountains Region. Materials show connections between individual Fellows' activities and larger social movements of the 1960s and 1970s, including the cultural identity and civil rights movements of Africa American, Native American, and Mexican American peoples.
Conditions Governing Access
Records more than 10 years old are open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
When requesting to view audiovisual material, please refer to the Title and the AV Number (example: AV 1916). Researchers are asked to check the "Restrictions" note for each Title. If a Title does not currently have an access copy, please contact a RAC archivist for further instruction.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers papers were transferred to, and accessioned by, RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necesary.
This material was transferred to the RAC in 2017 by the Ford Foundation and ingested by the RAC as Accession 2017:027.
Biographical / Historical
The Ford Foundation was chartered by Henry and Edsel Ford in 1936 "to receive and administer funds for scientific, educational and charitable purposes, all for the public welfare", and initially served the Ford family's charitable interests in the Detroit area. Following the deaths of Edsel Ford (1943) and Henry Ford (1947), the Foundation was propelled to the forefront of philanthropy as the largest American foundation in terms of both endowment and yearly expenditures, and with an international scope to its major program areas.
During the Foundation's first twenty years its major programs were in international economic development, primary and higher education, educational and public broadcasting, behavioral sciences, civil liberties, urban development, fine arts and the humanities. The Ford Foundation also partnered with the Rockefeller Foundation in supporting agricultural development in South America, Africa, and Southeast Asia. Since the 1970s, the Foundation has also pioneered programs in women's rights, energy policy, micro-financing in under-developed countries, establishing human rights groups, and improving international HIV/AIDS education.
Biographical / Historical
Established in 1966, the Ford Foundation's Leadership Development Program sought to provide fellowships to American community leaders working in the areas of education, social work, economic development, and political organization. Most LDP fellowships lasted for a year, and Fellows exercised a large amount of freedom in designing their individual program years. These programs consisted of internships, academic courses, workshops, site visits, conferences, and volunteer placements that would all provide opportunities for Fellows to learn and develop as community leaders. placements that would all provide opportunities for Fellows to learn and develop as community leaders. Ford required Fellows to submit both narrative and financial reports to their specific Regional Representative/Program Consultants in order to document their program progress and allowed expenses. The foundation started to phase out the program in 1975 due to a belief that the program's objective had been achieved as well as to a shift in the foundation's annual spending (David Nevin, "Left-Handed Fastballers: Scouting and Recruiting America's Grass-Roots Leaders"). The LDP ceased to operate in 1977.
The LDP was organized into four regional offices: 1) Region-at-Large; 2) Northeast; 3) Southwest; and 4) Southeast. Each regional office recruited Fellows from the geographic area that its title represented with the Region-at-Large Office chiefly selecting Fellows from Alaska, the Northwestern states, and the Appalachian Mountains Region. Most Fellows were teachers and school administrators, but there were also social workers and various types of community organizers selected for LDP Fellowships. Fellows generally originated from the types of communities in which they sought to become leaders and had strong personal investments in the issues they sought to address. Many of these communities were disempowered economically, socially, and politically. Several represented different minority populations throughout the country such as Native American, Mexican American, and African American communities in various geographic areas. Regional LDP Offices prioritized knowledge of community issues, demonstrated work in helping communities, and perceived leadership qualities in selecting individuals for fellowships. In order to be accepted to the program, Fellows needed to possess a capacity for personal initiative (Nevin).
Although Fellows primarily focused on developing local solutions to problems facing their particular communities, their program years consisted largely of travel to other areas where they could broaden their perspectives and assist other groups. This travel connected them with regional, national, and federal organizations trying to address the larger issues that impacted their home communities. Thus, many Fellows' program activities and later post-fellowship careers intersected heavily with significant U.S. social movements of the 1960s and 1970s. These movements include the cultural identity and civil rights movements of Native Americans, Mexican Americans, and African Americans. Student protests impacted a large number of LDP fellowships.
Ford invested more than eleven million dollars into the LDP throughout the course of the program's lifespan (Nevin). While one-year fellowship were generally the norm, the LDP also issued short-term fellowships that lasted for a few months.
Other Finding Aids
Other available finding aids describing the Ford Foundation's Leadership Development Program include:
FA650 Ford Foundation records, Leadership Development Program, Administrative Files
Arrangement
The collection is divided into five series and fourteen subseries.
The first four series consist entirely of Ford Foundation Leadership Development Program Fellow files, while the fifth series contains miscellaneous materials related to the Ford Foundation in general.
In regards to the first four series, each one contains the Fellow files of a particular Regional LDP Office. The order of the offices within the collection is as follows: 1. Region-at-Large; 2. Northeast; 3. Southwest; and 4. Southeast. Within each of these series, files are generally arranged in the ascending alphabetical order of the different LDP Fellows' surnames. Each individual LDP Fellow generally has two corresponding Fellow files.
The series were then broken into smaller subseries (two subseries for Series 1 and four subseries for Series 2, 3, and 4) during processing in order to improve user access to the large number of files produced by each Regional Office.
The fifth series has no subseries.
The collection arrangement is as follows:
Series 1. Region-at-Large LDP Fellow files, 1968-1979
Series 1 Subseries 1. A-M, 1968-1979
Series 1 Subseries 2. N-Z, 1968-1977
Series 2. Northeast Region LDP Fellow files, 1966-1977
Series 2 Subseries 1. A-F, 1966-1976
Series 2 Subseries 2. G-M, 1966-1976
Series 2 Subseries 3. N-S, 1967-1977
Series 2 Subseries 4. T-Z, 1967-1975
Series 3. Southwest Region LDP Fellow files, 1967-1980
Series 3 Subseries 1. A-F, 1967-1977
Series 3 Subseries 2. G-M, 1967-1977
Series 3 Subseries 3. N-S, 1967-1980
Series 3 Subseries 4. T-Z, 1967-1977
Series 4. Southeast Region LDP Fellow files, 1960-1979
Series 4 Subseries 1. A-F, 1960-1978
Series 4 Subseries 2. G-M, 1966-1978
Series 4 Subseries 3. N-S, 1966-1978
Series 4 Subseries 4. T-Z, 1963-1979
Series 5. Miscellaneous materials, 1971-1972
Original order was maintained as much as possible throughout the collection.
Adult education; African Americans; African Americans -- Civil rights; Agriculture, Cooperative; Alcoholism; Appalachian Region; Civil rights; Communities; Community leadership; Community-based social services; Consumer education -- United States; Cooperation; Curriculum change; Day care centers; Discrimination in education; Drug addiciton; Early childhood education; Education -- Study and teaching; Education, Bilingual; Educational leadership; Environmental education; Housing; Individualized instruction; Interpersonal relations; Leadership; Mexican Americans; Mexican Americans -- Civil rights; Minorities -- Housing; Native Americans; Political participation; Progressive education; Public service television programs; Race relations; School administrators; School integration; School management and organization; Sexual health; Social workers; Students -- Civil rights; Special education; Suffrage; Teachers -- Training of; Vocational education; Youth--Services for
- Region-at-Large LDP Fellow files, 1968-1979; 1; 3.3 Cubic Feet About 7.5 LTR size Hollinger boxes
  Scope and Contents
  The series consists entirely of Fellow files for the Leadership Development Program Region-at-Large Office. For the most part, these files follow the general organizational scheme imposed by the records' creators for all Fellow files documenting the LDP. This means that most Region-at-Large Fellows have two files for their associated records: One file holding original narrative reports submitted to Region-at-Large Regional Representative/Program Consultant Paul Nachtigal by the individual Fellow and one file holding narrative report copies submitted to the Ford Foundation by Nachtigal's office. The Region-at-Large files are also comprised of the same type of content as the rest of the Fellow files found within the collection. In addition to narrative reports, they chiefly contain correspondence between Nachtigal and individual Fellows, correspondence between Nachtigal and Ford LDP staff, and correspondence between Nachtigal and organizations that provided internships and other learning opportunities to LDP Fellows. Correspondence generally regards submissions of reports, fellowship progress, fellowship changes, and post-fellowship activities.
  The LDP Region-at-Large Selection Committee recruited Fellows from the states of Alaska, Colorado, Florida, Idaho, Illinois, Kansas, Kentucky, Louisiana, Missouri, Montana, North Dakota, South Dakota, North Carolina, Oklahoma, Oregon, Tennessee, Virginia, West Virginia, Washington, Wisconsin, and Wyoming. The Highlander Research and Education Center, a social justice leadership training program and cultural center in Tennessee, proved to be a popular internship placement for LDP Fellows of this region.
  Many Region-at-Large LDP Fellows focused on developing and improving the economic, education, political, and community organization resources of Appalachian and Native American populations. The series documents the emphasis on arts, culture, and history within the work of Fellows serving both types of communities. For example, several Fellow files contain records concerning Appalachian folklore, folk schools, and oral histories while others contain records concerning Native American crafts and cultural objects. Furthermore, the materials collected in some Appalachia-focused Fellow files document the use of audiovisual technologies and public broadcast television as tools for education and community organization. Sample classroom materials, pamphlets, and other types of records provide evidence of Fellows investigating, supporting, and establishing bilingual and bicultural programs for Native American children.
  Environmental issues provide another link between the records of the Appalachian Fellows and the records of the Native American Fellows. Within the series, there are a number of Fellow files that document the conflict between local Appalachian communities and strip-mining companies as well as the efforts of some communities to protect the health of their coal miners and combat Black Lung Disease. Conversely, there are a number of Fellow files that document the efforts of Native American communities to assert land claims and contest oil company interests.
  Other files in the series show that the remainder of the Region-at-Large LDP Fellows chiefly worked with African American and Mexican American communities.
  In addition to correspondence and reports, the series holds pamphlets, newsletters, promotional documents, draft classroom exercise materials and learning tools, press clippings, and one audio recording.
  Arrangement
  This series was broken into two subseries during processing in order to improve user access to the large number of files produced by the Region-at-Large Office.
  The series arrangement is as follows:
  Series 1 Subseries 1. A-M, 1968-1979
  Series 1 Subseries 2. N-Z, 1968-1977
  - A-M, 1968-1979; 1; 2.2 Cubic Feet About 5 LTR size Hollinger Boxes
    Subseries contains Fellow files for Region-at-Large Leadership Development Program Fellows whose last names begin with the letters A-M.
    - John, Adam - Anchorage, Alaska, 1968-1971 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      LDP Fellow: 1970-1971
      Original folder subheadings include:
      1. Reports
    - Allen, Henry L. - Tonkawa, Oklahoma, 1971-1974 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      LDP Fellow: 1971-1972
    - Allen, Henry L. - Tonkawa, Oklahoma, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Branscome, James - Berea, Kentucky, 1968-1975 (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
      LDP Fellow: 1968-1969
    - Brewer, Colleen - Pine Ridge, South Dakota, 1973-1976 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      LDP Fellow: 1973-1974
    - Brewer, Colleen - Pine Ridge, South Dakota, 1973-1976 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Brooks, Portia F.; Jackson, Tennie B.; and Ernest Riggins, 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Carpenter, Ted - Baxter, Tennessee, 1970-1974 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Carpenter, Ted - Baxter, Tennessee, 1969-1976; File includes a still image of LDP Fellow Ted Carpenter and his wife at a community meeting. (Box 1, Folder 10-11)
    - Coleman, Faye - Greensboro, North Carolina, 1972-1975 (Box 2, Folder 12)
      LDP Fellow: 1972-1973
    - Coleman, Faye - Greensboro, North Carolina, 1972-1975 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Ducheneaux, Gregory - Rapid City, South Dakota, 1973-1979 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Ducheneaux, Gregory - Rapid City, South Dakota, 1973-1979 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Dukes, Joyce - Knoxville, Tennessee, 1971-1975 (Box 2, Folder 16)
      1. Narrative Reports
    - Dukes, Joyce - Knoxville, Tennessee, 1971-1973 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Easterling, Edith - Pikeville, Kentucky, 1968-1973 (Box 2, Folder 18)
      LDP Fellow: 1969-1970
    - Easterling, Edith - Pikeville, Kentucky, 1969-1973 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Elliott, Annie - Largo, Florida, 1973-1975 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Elliott, Annie, Largo, Florida, 1973-1975 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Estes, Gary - Blacksburg, Virginia, 1971-1973 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Estes, Gary - Blacksburg, Virginia, 1970-1972 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Favel, Robert - Box Elders, Montana, 1970-1971 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Favel, Robert - Box Elders, Montana, 1970-1973 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Fire Thunder, Betty - Porcupine, South Dakota, 1974-1977 (Box 2, Folder 26)
      LDP Fellow: 1974-1975
    - Fire Thunder, Betty - Porcupine, South Dakota, 1974-1975 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Garcia, Gerald F. - Denver, Colorado, 1973-1974 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Garcia, Gerald F. - Denver, Colorado, 1972-1974 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Gilmore, Earl - Clinchco, Virginia, 1972-1974 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Gillette, Vance - Emmet, North Dakota, 1973-1974 (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Gillette, Vance - Emmet, North Dakota, 1973-1976 (Box 3, Folder 32-33)
    - Gray, Gerald J. - Box Elder, Montana, 1970-1975 (Box 3, Folder 34)
      1. Reports:
      File contains a small group of classroom materials from the Rocky Boy Elementary School. These documents include a Key to the Cree Syllabic Characters, a draft picture book, and award certificates.
      Ford Foundation Leadership Development Program Fellow Gerald J. Gray served as the school's Principal during his fellowship program and then later became the Rocky Boy School District Superintendent.
      Separated Materials
      An untitled still image has been removed from the file for stabilization.
    - Gray, Gerald J. - Box Elder, Montana, 1970-1977 (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - Gray, Gerald J. - Box Elder, Montana, 1970-1971 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - Hamilton, James Jr. - Hughes, Alaska, 1970-1973 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - Hamilton, James Jr. - Hughes, Alaska, 1970-1973 (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - Harper, Dennis - Chicago, Illinois, 1973-1977 (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - Harper, Dennis - Chicago, Illinois, 1973-1974 (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - Herr, Mary A. - Clairfield, Tennessee, 1972-1976 (Box 4, Folder 41-43)
    - Herr, Mary A. - Clairfield, Tennessee, 1972-1974 (Box 4, Folder 44)
    - Hopkins, Peggy R. - Chapel Hill, North Carolina, 1973-1975 (Box 4, Folder 45)
    - Hopkins, Peggy R. - Chapel Hill, North Carolina, 1972-1975 (Box 4, Folder 46)
    - Huffman, Roy Lee - Eagle Rock, Virginia, 1971-1972 (Box 4, Folder 47)
    - Humes, David - Hayti, Missouri, 1970-1975 (Box 4, Folder 48)
    - Humes, David - Hayti, Missouri, 1970-1973 (Box 4, Folder 49)
    - Hurst, Joanne - Lawrence, Kansas, 1972-1977 (Box 4, Folder 50)
    - Hurst, Joanne - Lawrence, Kansas, 1971-1973 (Box 4, Folder 51)
    - Jennings, Mike - Fairbanks, Alaska, 1973-1975 (Box 4, Folder 52)
    - Jennings, Mike - Fairbanks, Alaska, 1972-1975 (Box 4, Folder 53)
    - Kline, Michael - Capon Bridge, West Virginia, 1972-1977 (Box 5, Folder 54)
    - Kline, Michael - Capon Bridge, West Virginia, 1971-1972 (Box 5, Folder 55)
    - Lerma, Carlos - Woodburn, Oregon, 1973-1977 (Box 5, Folder 56)
    - Lerma, Carlos - Woodburn, Oregon, 1973-1974 (Box 5, Folder 57)
    - Littlejohn, Hawk and Rose - Louisville, Tennessee, 1973-1976 (Box 5, Folder 58)
    - Lopez, Robert - Gilcrest, Colorado, 1972-1974 (Box 5, Folder 59)
    - Lopez, Robert - Gilcrest, Colorado, 1972-1973 (Box 5, Folder 60)
    - Maguire, Robert P. - Huslia, Alaska, 1970-1975 (Box 5, Folder 61)
    - Maguire, Robert P. - Huslia, Alaska, 1970-1973 (Box 5, Folder 62)
    - Mahone, Darrell and Linda - Berea, Kentucky, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 63)
    - Mahone, Darrell and Linda, - Berea, Kentucky, 1974-1975 (Box 5, Folder 64)
    - Martinez, Tom - Altus, Oklahoma, 1972-1977 (Box 5, Folder 65)